Up there with the best of the best.
Top Gun is a action, drama film directed by Tony Scott.
For Lieutenant Pete 'Maverick' Mitchell and his friend and co-pilot Nick 'Goose' Bradshaw, being
accepted into an elite training school for fighter pilots is a dream come true.
But a tragedy, as well as personal demons, will threaten
Pete's dreams of becoming an ace pilot.
Maverick, played by Tom Cruise.
Charlie, played by Kelly McGillis.
Ice, played by Val Kilmer.
Goose, played by Anthony Edwards.
Viper, played by Tom Skerritt.
Jester, played by Michael Ironside.
Top Gun is a 1986 American action drama film directed by Tony Scott and produced by Don
Simpson and Jerry Bruckheimer, with distribution by Paramount Pictures.
The screenplay was written by Jim Cash and Jack Epps Jr., and was inspired by an article titled "Top
Guns", written by Ehud Yonay and published in California magazine three years earlier.
It stars Tom Cruise as Lieutenant Pete "Maverick" Mitchell, a young
naval aviator aboard the aircraft carrier USS Enterprise.
He and his radar intercept officer, Lieutenant (junior grade) Nick "Goose" Bradshaw (Anthony Edwards), are given the chance to train
at the United States Navy's Fighter Weapons School (Top Gun) at Naval Air Station Miramar in San Diego, California.
Kelly McGillis, Val Kilmer and Tom Skerritt also appear in supporting roles.
When Top Gun was released on May 16, 1986, although its visual effects and soundtrack were
universally acclaimed, the film initially received mixed reviews from film critics.
Despite this, four weeks after its release, the number of theaters showing it increased by 45 percent, and it overcame initial critical
resistance to become a huge commercial hit, grossing $357.4  million dollars globally against a production budget of $15 million.
Top Gun was the highest-grossing domestic film of 1986, as well
as the highest-grossing film of 1986 worldwide.
The film maintained its popularity over the years and earned an IMAX 3D re-release in 2013, while the
retrospective critical reception became more positive, with the film also emerging as a cult classic.
Additionally, the soundtrack to the film has since become one of the most
popular film soundtracks to date, reaching 9× Platinum certification.
The film won both an Academy Award and a Golden Globe for
"Take My Breath Away" performed by Berlin.
In 2015, the United States Library of Congress selected the film for preservation in the National
Film Registry, finding it "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
A sequel, Top Gun: Maverick, in which Cruise and Kilmer reprised their roles, was released 36
years later on May 27, 2022 to widespread critical acclaim and commercial success.
The film explores themes of dying and death, secret love,
lovesickness, airplane, loss of loved one.
The tone is emotional.